<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Mattox Beckman</title>
    <description>Contact Info, Schedule, Useful(?) information, and Random Musings</description>
    <link>http://mccarthy.cs.iit.edu/mattox/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://mccarthy.cs.iit.edu/mattox/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2015 18:11:57 -0600</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2015 18:11:57 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>AMB #0 &amp;mdash; On Dijkstra and Writing</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I have long admired E.W. Dijkstra for his contributions to computer science, and his very precise
thinking and communication.  A while back I discovered that Dijkstra’s works are all online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found that he had a habit that will benefit me in two ways.  The habit was to write a series of
papers called “EWD’s” which often were unpublished, but instead were circulated to
various colleagues.  Some of these writings were theorems, some became papers, some were just
refections on things he had seen recently.  It reminds me of a blog, except that many of them were
hand-written.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dijkstra explained the benefit he derived from doing this in his
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cs.utexas.edu/users/EWD/transcriptions/EWD10xx/EWD1000.html&quot;&gt;thousandth entry&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;On a more contented note: I am reasonably pleased with life, about as pleased as we poor mortals
may be allowed to be, and in this contentment the EWD-series plays a major role. If there is one
“scientific” discovery I am proud of, it is the discovery of the habit of writing
without publication in mind. I experience it as a liberating habit: without it, doing the work
becomes one thing and writing it down becomes another one, which is often viewed as an unpleasant
burden. When working and writing have merged, that burden has been taken away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The habit is also liberating in a much more profound sense. I consider, for instance,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cs.utexas.edu/users/EWD/ewd09xx/EWD975.PDF&quot;&gt;EWD975 (pdf)&lt;/a&gt; on
the Theorem of Pythagoras—of all theorems!—a major achievement of the last
semester. It was an unadulterated pleasure to write it; one of its recipients called it
“absolutely bloody marvellous.” Had I only written with publication in mind, it would
never have seen the light of day.  Not only would aforementioned recipient have been denied his
enjoyment, I would have been so too: what I sent out was Sunday’s version, which I could
only write after the discovery that I could still improve on Saturday’s version, The only way to
discover that a neglected or ignored topic is worth writing about is to write about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first benefit I will gain from this series is that I now have a mentor.  A long time ago I
learned that if one wanted to learn to write well, then one should read things that were written
well.  I now have a large collection of well-written essays to read.  Further, the topics themselves
are very interesting in their own right (such as the above-mentioned Theorem of Pythagoras)!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second benefit is that I can emulate this habit.  I have thought before that writing just for
its own sake was an important habit, but rarely had I seen it done before now.  With this
encouragement, I will start my own series.  This will help me sharpen my thinking and communicate my
ideas with my colleagues.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2014 08:30:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://mccarthy.cs.iit.edu/mattox/amb/2014/12/09/on-dijkstra-and-writing/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://mccarthy.cs.iit.edu/mattox/amb/2014/12/09/on-dijkstra-and-writing/</guid>
        
        
        <category>amb</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
